The number of views has been declining.
影片的點閱率一直下滑
FIRE VS ICE
（火對冰）
The latest video, Gas flame vs Ice magic, seems unpopular.
上支都市瓦斯對冰魔法的影片 評價不好啊
The comments were harsh, like, "A pointless waste of resources."
留言都大罵那是在“浪費天然資源”
We must tighten up our budget from today.
從今天起不能再亂花錢了
I will stop bidding on online auctions.
我也會停止買網拍的
-What's that? -I got it at last.
-這是什麼？ -我終於入手了
This magazine listed the final result of SEGA SATURN readers' choice.
刊載了SEGA土星遊戲 讀者最終票選結果的雜誌
Unfortunately, I hadn't had the chance to see the results.
可惜我當時沒機會看到結果
COLLECTOR'S EDITION
（收藏版）
I couldn't die without knowing it.
沒看到之前不能死
Maybe this desire kept me alive in the harsh other world.
也許是這意志 讓我在嚴苛的異世界存活下來
Such a silly thing kept you alive?
這種無所謂的事情？
-Takafumi. -What?
-敬文 -咦？
The results are here.
結果就在這裡
The last page of SEGA SATURN's history is…
SEGA土星歷史的最後一頁…
SATURN GAMES ARE THE WORLD'S #1
（土星遊戲世界第一）
…in this magazine.
…就在這本雜誌裡
Stunningly, I don't care.
我沒興趣到連自己都吃驚
The very last game that came in the first place was…
最後得到第一名的遊戲是…
Are you reading it already?
已經要看了嗎？
Oh, the winner was a bishojo game ported from the PC version.
是從電腦版移植過來的美少女遊戲啊
I guess the results weren't what you hoped for.
這大概不是你期望的結果
No, I'm not complaining.
不，我對這遊戲沒意見
I can agree with the ranking as I read the reviews.
我看過評價，我可以接受這個名次
But I feel sad, as if I were watching wild, macho high-school boys
只是有種看到桀驁不羈的男高中生
getting tamed by girlfriends.
在戀愛攻防中淪陷的失落感
Really?
這樣啊
-Not really. -What?
-騙人的 -咦？
Guardian Heroes should have been number one!
第一名是《守護者列傳》才對吧
It adopted the fighting game system into a side-scroller while maintaining balance.
它把格鬥遊戲的系統 毫無破綻地融入橫向捲軸動作遊戲
Its innovation and perfection has got to be recognized!
好好評價它的新鮮度和完成度啦
197th place? What?
第197名？什麼？
197th place?
第197名？
UNCLE: YOU'RE FINE THE WAY YOU ARE
（舅舅：妳這樣很好啊）
GET HOME
（回家）
SOLD CHEAPER THAN A SCOURING PAD
（比菜瓜布便宜）
One of the original SATURN RPGs was placed in second.
第二名是土星的原創遊戲哦，RPG類型的
I didn't play RPG at all.
我其實完全沒在玩RPG遊戲
What?
咦？
The beginning went okay.
一開始還好
YOU NEED SALT TO KILL SLUGS
（打倒大蛞蝓需要鹽哦）
But I couldn't remember what I did the day before…
但我隔天會忘記上次玩到哪裡
WHY DO I NEED SALT?
（我為什麼需要鹽？）
…and got lost.
接著就沒頭緒了
Did you?
這樣啊
I mean, I had an encounter like an RPG game in the other world.
說起來，我在異世界 也遇過類似RPG的事件呢
What?
咦？
Icuras elran.
依丘拉絲愛爾蘭
You fucking orc. I won't lose to a fugly pig like you.
可惡，臭半獸人 我們不會輸給你這種醜豬的
What is this?
這是？
This was the time right after I arrived at the village.
這是我剛到村莊的時候
Let's fast-forward it.
快轉吧…
Uncle, whenever you got to a village, you found yourself in a battle.
舅舅，你每到一個村莊，都會陷入戰鬥耶
Well, in the flame shrine at the west end of the village,
其實在村莊西邊的炎之祠堂裡
the legendary blaze dragon has roused.
傳說中的魔炎龍復活了
The village will be burned down if we don't do anything.
再這樣下去，村莊會被燒得一乾二淨
The only way to slay the blaze dragon is using the Ice clan's god freezing sword.
要打倒魔炎龍 只能靠冰之一族代代相傳的凍神劍
However, the descendant of the Ice clan is a bit of a pain in the neck.
但是，冰之一族的後裔有點難以應付
Her name is Mabel.
這個女孩是梅貝爾
Unless we melt the ice, trapping her heart,
我們必須融解她被冰封的心靈
we can't break the seal of the god freezing sword.
才能解除凍神劍的封印
When I was little,
我小時候
I saw powa-powa blossoms with my mom at the top of Mount Marchid.
在馬爾基德山的山頂 跟媽媽一起看過波爾波爾花
That was beautiful.
真的好美哦
I went straight to the shrine of flame and slew the legendary blaze dragon.
然後我就直接去祠堂把魔炎龍打倒了
How come?
為什麼？
Seriously, it was hard. But I killed it after I got its offensive strategy down.
真的很辛苦耶 我努力記住牠的攻擊模式才打倒牠的
Not like that! You should've gone to Mount Marchid for powa-powa blossoms.
不是吧，你應該去馬爾基德山 摘波爾波爾花給她啊
I couldn't remember that.
那種流程我記不住啦
It's not that complicated.
沒有那麼難啦
What? You defeated the legendary blaze dragon?
咦？你打倒魔炎龍了？
Thank you very much.
非常感謝你
They were so grateful.
他們很感激哦
Yeah.
好吧
I got it.
我去應門
SEGA SATURN Console and 20 games.
SEGA土星主機和20個遊戲
Takafumi, was that a package delivery?
敬文，是宅配嗎？
Oh, well… this is…
這個嘛…這是…
It was a surprise gift for him, but he just said we've got to save up.
這是給他的驚喜 但他剛剛才說不能再亂花錢了
This…
這是…
What?
咦？
Is he happy or furious?
他是喜是怒？
It's a bit early, but happy birthday, Uncle.
雖然還有點早，祝你生日快樂，舅舅
Oh, by the way…
對了…
I found Guardian Heroes.
有《守護者列傳》哦
Want to play?
要一起玩嗎？
I worried in vain.
我白擔心了
For my uncle, spending money on a SEGA console can't be a waste.
對舅舅來說，買SEGA主機不可能是亂花錢
The town trampled down in Alien Storm looked like this.
在《異形風暴》裡 被外星人蹂躪過的街道就像這樣
When it is deserted and chilly,
路上都沒人，天氣又冷
I can feel the tension in the air.
皮膚都刺痛起來了
Yeah. It's totally different from New Year's Eve in the other world.
是啊，跟異世界的跨年夜有天壤之別
What? Uncle!
咦？舅舅
-Do you want to know? -Yes.
-有興趣嗎？ -有
"If aliens were to invade the earth now,
“如果外星人入侵地球
would you be an ordinary citizen who runs for your life, or"…
你會是四處逃竄的普通百姓，還是…？”
That was the tagline of the game.
這是當時的廣告詞
-Players, as one of the Alien Busters-- -No, not the game!
-玩家要化身為異形獵人… -不是這個啦
Is that a comic magazine?
那是漫畫雜誌嗎？
Yeah. I haven't spent New Year's Eve reading a manga in a long time.
對，我想好好回味看漫畫跨年的感覺
Can you follow the story after a 17-year break?
隔了17年，還看得懂嗎？
KochiKame would follow the same plot all the time.
《烏龍派出所》從哪開始看都行吧
KochiKame's serialization is over.
那部已經結束連載囉
Really? I never thought it would end.
它是會完結的漫畫嗎？
You won't find it.
你找不到它的啦
I'm more interested in the story of the other world than the manga.
比起漫畫，我對異世界的故事更有興趣
Not on the contents page either.
翻目錄也找不到啦
Seriously?
真的假的？
Icuras elran.
依丘拉絲愛爾蘭
It's not a big deal, but it's something like a New Year's Eve party.
也沒什麼大不了的 就像例行的跨年夜派對
It's a thanksgiving festival
為了感謝神保護他們跨冬而舉辦的祭典
The lord would feed you a splendid dinner.
領主會在這天宴請所有人
Cheers!
乾杯
That's some feast.
挺盛大的嘛
The residents of the other world were pumped up for this festival.
異世界的人在祭典期間很嗨哦
For the festival, I also…
在這一天，我也…
All right, we gonna have a great time!
好，各位，我們一起狂歡吧
Yeah!
好耶
Well, I wish I could be like that.
要是我有這種衝動就好了
I couldn't be a totally different person from who I was.
原本的性格到了異世界也不會突然改變
I ate alone and went back to my room.
我獨自吃過飯後，就回住宿處了
What?
咦？
It was great. I enjoyed the roasted chicken--
那道烤雞很好吃哦…
I'm not talking about the food. Was that all for the festival?
我不是在講味道啦 祭典就這樣結束了嗎？
-Yeah. -Where was she? The tsun--
-對 -那個傲…
The bad-mouthing girl?
毒舌的人呢？
She was not there, and nothing happened after that.
那傢伙當時不在那裡，後來也沒怎樣
Do you wanna play on the SATURN?
要不要來玩土星？
Let's do that!
好啊
Pew pew!
守護者…
You'll break the buttons.
你會把按鈕按壞啦
By the way, Mabel came to my room after the festival.
對了，祭典過後 梅貝爾有來住宿處找我哦
The protector of the god freezing sword.
凍神劍那個啊
Now, the battle begins!
好，戰鬥開始
-I thought we finally finished talking-- -Hurry up!
-好不容易才結束對話橋段… -快點
Well… nothing really happened.
咦？又沒發生什麼事
See?
你看
MEMORY - SHOW A PIECE OF YOURSELF
（顯現記憶片段吧）
Why are you here?
妳怎麼會在這裡？
I wanted you to tell me.
我想請教你…一件事
You slew the dragon single-handedly. I want to be strong like you.
你獨自打倒了魔龍，我想變得跟你一樣強
How can I stop being a coward?
我要怎麼捨棄糟糕的自己？
"Stop being a coward"?
“糟糕的自己”？
Who said that you are a coward?
是誰說妳糟糕的？
-What? -Who said that?
-咦？ -是誰說的？
The village mayor.
村長之類的
Live your life the way you want to,
別理別人決定的生活方式
not by someone else's ways.
人只要照自己的方式生活就好了
I believe strength is the power to carry this through.
我認為能貫徹這個信念就是所謂的堅強
Great. That's so cool, Uncle.
帥啊，太帥了，舅舅
Mabel being like this!
那樣的梅貝爾
Like this, Uncle must have gradually built relationships in the other world.
舅舅也一步一步地 跟異世界的夥伴進行內心的交流
How have you spent your life until now?
妳是怎麼活到現在的？
I have been a recluse and closed off my heart.
我把自己關在房裡，封閉著內心
That's fine.
那樣就行了
What? But…
咦？但是…
That's completely fine.
那樣就好了
No matter what people said, I never gave up being a SEGA user
別人再怎麼數落我 我都以身為SEGA玩家自豪
and never will.
今後也是
Is your role to be an ordinary citizen who buys a popular console?
妳是別人推薦什麼主機 就買什麼的普通人嗎？
Or…
還是…
Are you sure?
真的可以嗎？
Yes, I'm sure.
當然可以
Incredible!
太好了
-She chose her life and went back home. -I'm so happy to stay reclusive.
-她看清未來方向後，就回家了 -可以繼續家裡蹲了
Oh, she gave me the sword.
對了，她把劍給我了
-Please keep the god freezing sword. -Thanks, but no thanks. It's cold.
-請你收下凍神劍 -不了，太冰了
Really?
這樣啊
No, I declined the offer.
我拒絕了嗎？
Well… that's about it.
算了，大概就是這樣
Uncle, would you care for a bowl of soba noodles?
舅舅，來吃跨年蕎麥麵吧？
That's a good idea. Let's boil the water.
好主意，來燒開水吧
What did you do on New Year's Eve when you were a student? Play games?
你學生時代都怎麼跨年呢？打電動嗎？
Well, I watched TV. Something like an It's Okay to Laugh! special episode.
我會看電視 像是《笑一笑又何妨》特別節目
It was a special occasion as students couldn't watch daytime shows.
因為學生看不到平日的節目 感覺比較特別
That show ended too.
那個節目也停播了
Seriously? How is that possible?
真的假的？那節目會結束哦？
Finito.
會哦
Well, it's been 17 years. No wonder.
也是啦，都過了17年
But the show was on until three years ago.
但三年前還在播就是了
It lasted that long? That's awesome!
挺長壽的嘛，真厲害
-KochiKame ended last year. -What?
-《烏龍派出所》是去年結束的 -啥？
What kind of shows do you like, Takafumi?
你平常都看什麼節目？
I don't think you've watched it, but Not Okay to Laugh.
你應該沒看過吧，《不准笑》
No way! What happened with Tamori?
不會吧？塔摩先生怎麼了？
It's not the sequel.
那不是接檔的節目啦
It seems like he'd watched TV a lot.
沒想到舅舅滿常看電視的
Playing games, chatting, and slurping soba…
玩遊戲、閒聊、吃蕎麥麵…
and that's how the new year rolled in.
新的一年就這樣來了
JANUARY, 2018
（2018年1月）
The breeze you just made was quite sharp.
剛剛那陣風挺有勁的
Let's keep it that way all day today.
就是這種感覺，今天也請多指教囉
No way, you are kidding again.
不會吧，你又在開玩笑了
I should avoid this street from now on.
以後還是別走這條路好了
Fujimiya?
藤宮？
Takafumi?
敬文？
I thought so!
果然是妳
You can't be this tall!
怎麼會？
I hit a growth spurt in high school. It's been such a long time.
我進高中就長高了，好久不見
Yeah.
對啊
How are you doing these days?
最近好嗎？
A lot happened, and I'm working part-time.
發生不少事，我現在在打工
I see. I'm going to college.
這樣啊，我進了大學
It's chilly.
好冷
Do you wanna stop by my place? It's close by.
要來我家嗎？很近哦
Your parents' house?
老家嗎？
No.
不是
I'll come by after dropping off the groceries.
我先把東西放回家再過去
Okay, here is the address.
好，這是地址
30 MINUTES LATER
（30分鐘後）
Takafumi?
敬文？
TAKAFUMI: I'M GRABBING SOME SNACKS.
（敬文：我去買零食 妳先進去，門沒鎖）
Hi, I'm coming in.
打擾了…
Stonagas resto rarbarum.
斯托納卡斯雷司特拉帕爾姆
Icuras cuora.
依丘拉絲吉歐拉
Icuras cuora. Icuras cuora.
依丘拉絲吉歐拉…
Gotta use Japanese.
要用日語
-Spirits of memory, deliver unto oblivion. -Uncle!
-記憶的精靈啊，將它消去吧 -舅舅
Takafumi, the enemy… She saw it.
敬文，敵人…她看到了
Erase-- Erasing her memory faster,
得…早點把記憶消除掉
-means less impact on her mind. -She's my friend!
-對人格的影響比較小 -她是我朋友啦
A… friend?
朋友？
Thank you for being friends with Takafumi.
謝謝妳對敬文的照顧
-Well, that was… -I cast in Granbahamal lingo.
-所以… -我用異世界語施咒的
Like a dialect?
像方言嗎？
So, Takafumi is supporting an uncle who hasn't worked for 17 years.
所以說敬文現在在撫養 17年來都沒工作過的舅舅
I am a YouTuber.
我是YouTuber
I saw him mumbling to himself out there.
他剛剛在外面自言自語耶
Occasionally, I chat with spirits to sharpen my magic skills.
我偶爾會跟精靈交談，維持魔法的熟練度
He's seriously crazy!
他真的很不妙
Yes, it's crazy.
沒錯，很不妙
Because he returned from another world and does magic.
畢竟他從異世界歸來，還會用魔法嘛
I practice magic and my YouTube channel showcases it.
沒錯，我是這一型的YouTuber
Then do the goddamn magic now!
那你現在就用魔法啊
Well… I can't do it for free. I'm a YouTuber with two million views.
我好歹有兩百萬點閱率，要我免費表演…
-Right? -Yeah.
-對吧？ -對
What is the basis of his professionalism?
哪來的專業意識啊？
Anyway, you shouldn't hinder Takafumi's life anymore.
總之，請你別讓敬文的人生再脫離正軌了
Oh, I see.
這樣啊
You like Takafumi.
妳喜歡敬文是嗎？
No, no, no, no, no. It's not that.
不…沒這回事
100% no. We are just friends.
百分之百沒有，我們只是朋友
It shouldn't be the case. I understand mature love.
不可能，我很懂大人的戀愛
I watched the entire Evangelion series when I was in junior high.
我國中時看過整套《新世紀福音戰士》
You watched Eva?
你看過EVA？
Yes, I did. Everyone did.
看過啊，大家都在看
At that time, SEGA was one of the sponsors of Evangelion.
當時SEGA是其中一個節目贊助商
In the end, it's because of SEGA.
果然還是因為SEGA
Well, then you know Asuka too?
那你知道明日香囉？
The girl in the red suit, right?
穿紅色駕駛服那個吧？
Oh, shit! Uncle may catch on to the tsundere concept!
糟了，他會察覺到傲嬌的概念
Don't you misunderstand. You are indebted to me now.
別搞錯了，你欠我一次
That's not what I meant.
我不是那個意思
I didn't mean "together forever" or anything.
我不是要你陪我一輩子哦
He may realize what that elfin girl really meant.
他可能會發現那個精靈女孩的心意
Did you know?
你知道嗎？
Actually, Asuka has a crush on Kaji.
其實明日香喜歡加持先生哦
Sorry, Takafumi, you may be too inexperienced
敬文應該還沒辦法察覺
to notice her crush on Kaji.
她對加持先生的好感吧
What? Yeah.
咦？是啊
SO SHALLOW…!!!
（理解程度太膚淺了！）
Stop fooling around already.
你們給我適可而止
Don't make assumptions based on an anime's views on love.
別拿動畫的戀愛觀來妄下斷論啦
You're right. Let's talk about real love.
好吧，那我來說真正的愛
Her name was Kaede Nanase.
曾經有個叫七瀨楓的女生
The enemy stole her mind, and she lost her old self.
她被敵人奪走心智，再也不是過去的她了
Her affection soon turned into lethal intention in battle.
在戰鬥過程中 她的情感沒多久也轉變成殺意
However, after a long battle, she got a sure response.
但經過漫長的戰鬥，她的反應不容置疑
Joy.
喜悅
She regained herself under the bursting flash.
她在炸裂的閃光中回過神來
"Who did I kill?"
“我到底殺了誰？”
"What did I lose?"
“我失去了什麼？”
There is no such a thing as "too early" to express your affection.
如果要表白的話，永遠不嫌早哦
Oh, my God.
怎麼會…
The resolution gap between anime and games is too big.
動畫跟遊戲的解析度也差太多了吧
Hey, Fujimiya.
藤宮…
What?
幹嘛啦？
That was just a story from a video game.
那只是電視遊戲的劇情哦
Wow--
電…
-Just a fiction? -A fiction?
-騙我的？ -什麼騙妳？
No, I experienced it firsthand.
那是我的親身經驗
You, shut your…
請你適可而止…
Spirits of memory, investigate now.
記憶的精靈啊，立刻探究吧
"Geez, he has a roommate. I feel stupid for being psyched and changing my outfit."
“竟然有同居人 我還像白癡一樣換了衣服才來”
-What? -True, you're wearing a different outfit.
-什麼？ -真的換過衣服耶
No, it's the same one.
沒有換啦
You even took a shower.
妳還特地沖澡
No, I didn't.
我才沒有
Who is there?
是誰啊？
A mind reader, or con man?
讀心術？還是騙子？
What are you?
你到底是什麼人？
I am just an uncle…
我只是普通的大叔
back from another world--
從異世界歸來的…
Mr. Shibazaki, I got a package for you.
柴崎先生，有您的包裹
-Mr. Shibazaki? -I'm coming.
-柴崎先生？ -來了…
Mr. Shibazaki?
柴崎先生？
You've got to cut ties, Takafumi.
跟他斷絕關係吧，敬文
Seriously, you need to get out.
最好別跟他有所牽扯
If you can't afford the rent, I will cover it by taking on a job.
如果房租太貴，我可以打工幫你分攤
-Seriously? Want to be my roommate? -What?
-真的嗎？要跟我合租？ -咦？
-I see, that's definitely an option. -Well, I didn't mean that--
-對哦，跟藤宮合租也不錯 -我不是那個意…
But I've got my uncle with me.
不過我畢竟有舅舅在
What's in there? This box weighs 15 kilograms.
這是什麼啊？竟然有15公斤
-It's a bag of rice. -Rice?
-是米 -米？
Can you accept my scribbled signature?
我隨便亂簽也可以嗎？
One additional person now knows my uncle in real life.
在現實世界中認識舅舅的人又多了一個
He looked somewhat more cheerful than his usual self.
不知為何，舅舅今天看起來比平常更開心
And I'll refrain from buying rice online…
我也會克制利用網購買米的行為…
I felt a lethal intent.
我感覺到殺氣了
Subtitle translation by: Naoka Matsumura
字幕翻譯：宋梅君